24. Free-running. Running, urban, acrobatics, and tricks. Do those words seem to go together?
If so, you may be a free-runner. Free-runners have taken tricks that are usually performed
with a prop or at least a net and moved them into their daily lives and into public view.
Free-running is a way of interacting with the urban landscape in an unusual way. Free-runners
use the city as a gym. Instead of following the typical paths or doing typical movements,
free-runners use urban obstacles as props for acrobatic tricks. Free-running is related
to the French idea of parkour, but parkour is about efficiency, speed, and self-preservation,
while free-running is more about fun. The free-running environment contains high and
low walls, stairs, ramps, bars and fences, arches, and doorways. Therefore, most free-running
moves are designed to use these elements. There are a variety of different vaults for
getting over low walls. There are running techniques to help scale high walls and flips
to get down off them. Dives, rolls, and twists help protect the body when landing. And of
course, there are tons of ways to make each move more difficult, more athletic, and more
pleasing to watch. All of these stunts are the reason free-running competitions are often
held within larger, stunt competitions. There are more and more competitions dedicated solely
to free-running, however. There are free-running clubs in many urban areas, and free-running
fans are now active in many of the world's cities. If you see urban obstacles you can
jump over, climb, or duck under, then there are probably free-runners in your city too.